Guide to the Charles Henry Hall Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charles Henry Hall Papers
1844-1895
RG 94
Yale University Divinity School Library
15
(38 boxes)
More than 1500 manuscript sermons and other writings document Hall's work as a clergyman. Charles Henry Hall (1820-1895) was an Episcopal clergyman in New York, South Carolina, and Washington D.C.
Hall, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1820-1895
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1820 Nov 7 Born in Georgia
1842 B. A., Yale College.
1843-1844 Studied Biblical literature in Andover, MA, and at General Theological Seminary, NY
1844 Ordained as deacon in Protestant Episcopal Church
1845 Took charge of St. John's Church, Huntington, LI
1847-1848 Rector of Church of the Holy Innocents, West Point, NY
1848-1856 Rector of St. John's Church, St. John's Island, SC
1856-1869 Rector of Church of the Epiphany, Washington, DC
1869- 1895 Rector of Church of the Holy Trinity, Brooklyn, NY
1895 Sep 12 Died
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life and work of Charles Henry Hall, a prominent Episcopal clergyman during the second half of the nineteenth century. Hall was a strong Unionist during the Civil War, though the church he served in Washington during this period was divided in its sentiments. He was a leading citizen of Brooklyn, NY, serving as civil service commissioner and park commissioner. He was a close friend of Henry Ward Beecher. Hall generally avoided political matters in the pulpit but did speak on civic and social reforms.
The Sermons of Series I provide very thorough documentation of Hall's preaching More than 1500 manuscript sermons are in a numbered sequence that corresponds roughly to chronological order. Dates and places preached are noted on most of the sermons. The numbered sequence is followed by four volumes of indexes to the sermons, which refer to sermons preached on various texts and topics.
The Notes and Writings of Series II include unnumbered, published, and fragmentary sermons, lectures, addresses, and notes. The bound volumes in this series include volumes of notes and quotations, a parish register from the Church of the Epiphany, Washington, DC, two letter copybooks, and a visiting book. Series III, Biographical Documentation, primarily contains tributes following Hall's death.
Arrangement
I. Sermons, 1844-1895
II. Notes and Writings, 1848-1893, n.d.
III. Biographical Documentation, 1895, n.d.
Clergy; Hall, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1820-1895; Episcopal Church -- Clergy
- Sermons, 1844-1895; Series I
  - #1 - 40, 1844-1845 (Box 1)
  - #41 - 70, 1845-1846 (Box 2)
  - #71 - 120, 1846-1848 (Box 3)
  - #121 - 179, 1848-1850 (Box 4)
  - #180 - 237, 1851-1853 (Box 5)
  - #238 - 320, 1853-1857 (Box 6)
  - #321 - 369, 1857-1858 (Box 7)
  - #370 - 419, 1858-1859 (Box 8)
  - #420 - 475, 1859-1860 (Box 13)
  - #476 - 535, 1860-1861 (Box 14)
  - #536 - 584, 1861-1863 (Box 15)
  - #586 - 639, 1863-1864 (Box 16)
  - #640 - 689, 1864-1865 (Box 9)
  - #690 - 750, 1865-1867 (Box 10)
  - #751 - 796, 1868-1869 (Box 11)
  - #797 - 853, 1869-1872 (Box 12)
  - #855 - 903, 1872-1873 (Box 21)
  - #904 - 956, 1873-1875 (Box 22)
  - #957 - 999, 1875-1876 (Box 23)
  - #1000 - 1025, 1876 (Box 24)
  - #1026 - 1055, 1876-1878 (Box 17)
  - #1056 - 1089, 1878 (Box 18)
  - #1090 - 1134, 1879-1880 (Box 19)
  - #1135 - 1199, 1880-1882 (Box 20)
  - #1200 - 1249, 1882-1884 (Box 25)
  - #1250 - 1310, 1884-1885 (Box 26)
  - #1311 - 1359, 1885-1886 (Box 27)
  - #1360 - 1414, 1886-1888 (Box 28)
  - #1415 - 1474, 1888-1889 (Box 29)
  - #1475 - 1524, 1889-1895 (Box 30)
  - #1525 - 1581, 1895 (Box 31)
  - Indexes to sermons (Box 32)
- Notes and Writings, 1848-1893, n.d.; Series II
  - Miscellaneous - loose sheets, 1851- 1893 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous - loose sheets, n.d. (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous - loose sheets, n.d. (Box 35)
  - Four bound volumes: notes (Box 36)
  - Parish register: Church of the Epiphany, Washington, DC, 1857-1864 (Box 37)
  - Bound volume: Lectures on the Epistle of St. James; in bound volume also containing notes by Annie M. Hall, 1848-1852 (Box 37)
  - Bound volume: Visiting Book, 1858-1867 (Box 37)
  - Bound volumes: two letter copybooks, 1870s-1885 (Box 37)
  - Bound volume: notes (Box 37)
- Biographical Documentation, 1895, n.d.; Series III
  - Tributes, obituary (Box 38, Folder 156)